Guide to the Max V. Mathews Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Max V. Mathews papers
1953-2011
SC1107
Mathews, Max V.
20.5 Linear feet (16 boxes)
Correspondence, articles, lab notebooks, musical scores, audio recordings, computer files, and other materials related to the professional work of computer music pioneer Max V. Mathews.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
This collection was given to Stanford University, Special Collections, by Marjorie Mathews in April 2012.
Information about Access
Computer files are closed pending processing; otherwise the materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical Note
Max V. Mathews, often cited as "the father of computer music," was born in Columbus, NE on November 13, 1926. After training as a radio technician in the Navy, he attended the California Institute of Technology, where he received a bachelor's degree in electrical engineering in 1950. He received a Ph.D. from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1954.
Mathews joined the Bell Labs acoustical and behavioral research department in 1955. While there, he developed a computer program that allowed an IBM mainframe to compose and play a 17 second composition. Subsequent versions of this program, called Music, led to the development of popular computer music software such as CSounds and CMix, as well as MAX, a programming language for music named in his honor. Mathews was also the inventor of the Radio Baton, an electronic device for control of music in Midi format, and several electric violins. His collaborators included composers John Cage and Pierre Boulez. In the 1970s, he assisted Boulez in establishing the Institut de Recherche et Coordination Acoustique/Musique in Paris.
Mathews directed the acoustical and behavioral research center at Bell Labs from 1962 to 1985, at which time he accepted the position of Professor of Music (Research) at Stanford University. While at Stanford, he was affiliated with the Center for Computer Research in Music and Acoustics. Following his retirement as Professor Emeritus in 2005, he remained active in the electronic music field until his death on April 21, 2011.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence, articles, lab notebooks, musical scores, audio recordings, computer files, and other materials related to the professional work of computer music pioneer Max V. Mathews. Correspondents of note include Jean-Claude Risset and Pierre Boulez. Also included are several films by Lillian Schwartz with music by Mathews.
Access Terms
Bell Telephone Laboratories.; Boulez, Pierre, 1925-; Cage, John; IRCAM (Research institute: France).; Knowlton, Kenneth C.; Mathews, Marjorie; Risset, Jean-Claude; Schwartz, Lillian F., (Lillian Feldman), 1927-; Stanford University. Center for Computer Research in Music and Acoustics.; Stanford University. Department of Music.; Audiotapes.; Audiovisual.; Computer music.; Electronic music; Electronic musical instuments; Music--Acoustics and physics.; Slides.; Videorecordings.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence
  - Abbott, Curtis (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alonso, Sydney (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Acoustical Society of America (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Appleton - Pacific Rimbombo (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Appleton (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Appleton - Duobatone (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Appleton - Tres Canciones Cubanas - 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Arfib (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Austin, Larry (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Audio Eng Society (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Babbitt, Milton (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Babbitt, Milton - Phonemeua (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bauman, Marcia (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Barriere, Francoise (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Barierre, Jean-B. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Beethoven Piano Concerto #2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Beauchamp, James (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bennett, Gerald and Vrena (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Beranek, Leo (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bharncha, Jamshed (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bodin, Lars-Gunnar (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Boesch, Rainer (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bohlen, Heinz (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bosch, Josefina (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Boie, Bob, Patric (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Boulanger, Richard (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Boulanger - Solemn Song for Evening - Master Copy (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Boulanger - Shadows - Master Copy of Score (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Boulanger - Radio Sonata (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Boulanger - Solemn Song 3 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Boulanger - Maptime etc. - winter 1999 - Interval (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Boulanger - Shadows (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bourges Academy (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bregman, Albert (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Brooks, Jim (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Brophy, J. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Burtner (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Buxton, William (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Cadoz, Claude (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Caipirinha Productions (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Cage, John (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Cal Tech Distinguished Alumni Award (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Carey - Aqui (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - CBS (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Chadabe (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Chowning, Marianne (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Chowning, John (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Chrysler Corp. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Ciamaga, Gustav (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Ciane, Suzanne (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Cohen, Elizabeth (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Computer Music - Scientific American Paper (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Cook, Perry (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - CSIRAC 1951 Computer Music (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - CS+E Board, National Academy of Sciences (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Davies, Hugh (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Dannenberg, Roger (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Dieuer, Glen (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Dodge, Charles (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Dutry (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Einaudi, Andrew (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Errante, F. Gerald (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Fant, Gunnar (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Flaunagan, Jim (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Freed, Adrian (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Fujimura, Osamu (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Gabaro, Kenneth (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Garrard, Mimi (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Gershenfeld (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Ghent - Valery (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Gurevich, Michael (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Gibiau (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Guttman, Newman (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Hamilton, Robert (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Haynes, Stanley (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Hewlett, Walter (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Hiller, Lejaren (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Hogg, David (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Horowitz, Israel (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Hutchins, Carleen (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Hutter, Marissa (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - IEEE (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Ishii, Kenichiro (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Jaffe, David (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Julesz, Bela (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Kahrs, Mark (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Kimura, Mari (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Kobrin, Ed (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Kropfl, Francisco (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Krumhausl, Carol (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Kulowski, Andrzej (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Lansky, Paul (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Laske, Otto (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Leslie, Grace (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Levitin, Dan (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Logemann, George (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Le Caine, Hugh (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Lewin, David (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Machover, Tod (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Majors, Art (Peru Achievement Foundation) (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Mac Innis, Donald (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Mak, Clarence (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Martin, D. W. (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - McDermott, Suzanne (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - McGill, William (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Metzner, Jim (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Milenkovic, Paul (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Miller, G. L. (Laurie) (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Miller, Joan (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Molava, Pamela (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Moles, Abraham A. (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Moog, R. A. (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Moore, F. R. (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Morrill, Dexter (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Morrison, Julia (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Musical Styles - Pref Space - Ideal Points (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Music Compositions by Max Mathews (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Music from Math record (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Music V (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Marrin, Teresa Nakra (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - NASA Talk, 11/87 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National Academy of Engineering (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - National Academy of Sciences (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Negyesy, Janos (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Nichols, Charles (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Noll, A. M. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nelson, Robert (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Oliveros, Pauline (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - O'Donnel, Martin (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Olson, Harry (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Oppenheim, Daniel (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Paik, June N. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Palmer, Caroline (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Paradiso, Joseph (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Perkins, Leeman (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Peterzell, Paul (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Pierce, John (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Pickering, Norman (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Pioneers (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Plantinga, Leon (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Plomp (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Prestia, Chrysa (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Puckette, Miller (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Pulfer, J. K. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Qwartz Award, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Quate, Calvin (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Radio Baton CD (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Radunskaya, Ame (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - RCA Synthesizer (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Redfern, Nancy (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Reeves, Alyson (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Rhea, Thomas (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Risset, Jean-Claude (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
  - Risset Violin Concerto - Schemes (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Reynolds, Roger (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Robb, Donald (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Roberts, Arthur (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Roberts, Lynda (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Roederer, Juan G. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Rossing, Thomas (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Rudow, Vivian (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Rhee, Tom (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Schaeffer, Pierre (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Scavone, Gary (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Schroeder, Marconi nomination (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Smith, Julius (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Smith, Leland (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Society for Electro-Acoustic Music (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Soley, David (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Spiegel, Laurie (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Stanford (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Stibitz, George (Box 2, Folder 56-57)
  - Stokowski, Leopold (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Sapp, Craig (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Sarnoff Award (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Scavone, Gary (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Schwartz, Elliott (Box 2, Folder 62-63)
  - Scientific American (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Seawright, Andrew (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Seawright, James (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Scherchen, Hermann (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Schloss, Andy (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Schroeder, Manfred (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Schwarz, Gerald (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Shadle, Chris (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Shapiro, Gerald (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Shinoda, Haruko (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Shyu, Ruth (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Slawson, A. W. (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Slepian, Don (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Strang, Gerald (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Strong, William J. (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Strasser, Bruce (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Sundberg, Johan (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - System Development Foundation (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Taylor, Charles A. (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Technology, Telephones, and Art (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Tenney, Jim (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Theremin Center, Moscow (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Thompson, Ken (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Thompson, Molly (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Thompson, Tim (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Tubbesing, Victor (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Turetsky, Burt (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Ussachevsky, V. (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Vanderbeek, Stan (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Varesze, Edgard (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Verco, Scott (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Vercoe, Barry (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Waisvicz, Michel (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Warzyuek, John (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Wessel, David (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - West, Jim (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Wilson, R. S. (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Winckel, Fritz (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Winkler, Tod (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Xenakis, Iannis (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - York, Carl (SDF) (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Young, Gayle (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Zinovieff, Peter (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Zeta (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Zukofsky, Paul (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Patents
  - Bender Violin Pickup, circa 1988-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - Boie Drum (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
- Lectures, performances, and articles
  - Groove (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hugh Le Caine Paper (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Cage Piece for Philharmonic (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Mirages (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Poles and Zeroes of Vocal Tract (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Violin Resources (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - AAAS, Philadelphia, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Dumb Ways to Play Smart Instruments, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Real Time Performance, Stockholm, 1985 Sep (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Lincoln Labs talk, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Rutgers Talk, Small Computers in Arts, 1988 Nov (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Japan Trip, 1989 Apr (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - ICMC, Ohio, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - AAAS, New Orleans, 1990 Feb (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - AAAS, Washington, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - ASA, 1990 May (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Brown University, 1991 Apr (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Stanford Library Visiting Committee, 1991 Feb (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - CCRMA Associates, 1991 May (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Cuba, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - AIX Concert, 1991 Jun (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Bourges, 1991 Jun (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - ICRAM, 1991 Jun (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - AES, 1991 Jun (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Thermin Concert, Frost, 1991 Sep 27 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - ICMC, 1991 Oct (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - SEAMUS, 1991 Oct (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - ASA, 1991 Nov (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Boston and Dartmouth, 1991 Nov 17-18 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Alea Pierce, 1991 Dec 3 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Santa Catalina Demo, 1991 Dec 5 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Music Representation, Stanford, 1991 Jan (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - L.A. Musical Psychoacoustics, 1991 Feb (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Columbus and Bowling Green, 1992 Mar 13-16 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Newcomp, Boston, 1992 Feb 15 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - CCRMA Associates Talk, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Buenos Aires, 1992 Jun (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Woods Hole, 1992 Jul 26 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - ICMC, Computers and Performance, 1992 Oct 16 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - College Music Society, San Diego, 1992 Oct 29 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - University of Virginia, 1992 Nov 2 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - ASA, New Orleans, 1992 Nov 4 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Arizina State University, Boulanger Concert, 1992 Nov 9 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - University of Victoria, 1993 Jan 13 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Music Library Meeting, 1993 Feb 5 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - San Diego, 1993 Apr 22 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Affiliates Meeting, 1993 May (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Hong Kong, 1993 Oct (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Scream Concert, 1993 Nov 13 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - San Jose Children's Museum, 1993 Nov 17 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Bell Labs Research Colloqium, 1993 Dec 10 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Santa Catalina, 1994 Jan 5 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Technology and Society, 1994 Mar 8 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - IBM, GE, RPI, Skidmore, 1994 Mar 18-25 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - SEAMUS and Bennington, 1994 Apr 5 and 8 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Media Lab Talk, 1994 Oct 20 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Boston ASA Chapter, 1994 Oct 25 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Pomona Lecture and Concert, 1995 Feb 4 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - San Jose Chamber Music Society, 1995 Mar 12 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Wellesley, 1995 Apr 10 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - CCRMA Affiliates, 1995 May 10 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Colgate Gigs, 1995 Oct 11-19 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Moscow / Bourges, 1995 Jun (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Bourges, IRCAM, Marsaille, 1996 Jun (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - CCRMA Concert, 1996 Oct 24 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Indiana, 1997 Mar 8 and 9 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - 3-Symphonic States - Stanford Symphony and Baton, 1997 May 30 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Bourges, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Woods Hole Concert, 1997 Jul (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Brasilia Lectures, 1997 Aug (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - NTT Symposium and Concert, 1997 Nov 13 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - LIPM, 1998 Mar 18 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Creating Intellectual Property, 1998 Sep 26 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Old Bell Labs Art Talk, 1998 Nov 8 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - University of Missouri, Computer Music History, 1999 Mar 10 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Media Lab, 1999 May 21 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Bourges, 1999 Jun (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - ZKM History Talk, 2000 Sep 11 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Dartmouth, 2001 Oct 19 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - McGill and University of Montreal, 2001 Mar 23 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - CHI Workshop, Seattle, 2001 Apr 1-2 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Zurich Lectures, 2001 Apr 23-May 4 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Japan Trip, NTT and eAT, 2002 Feb (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Transparent Tape Festival, 2002 Aug 16-18 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Computer Music History Talk, transparencies (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Music V Overheads (from Technology of Computer Music book) (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Radio - Baton, transparencies (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Improv Program, transparencies (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Computer Typesetting, transparencies (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Playboy Violin, transparencies (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Conductor Program, transparencies (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Sequential Drum, transparencies (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Pierce - Scale, transparencies (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Miscellaneous transparencies (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Index to Articles (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Articles, #1, #3-10 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Articles, #11-15 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Articles, #16-22 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Articles, #23-25 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Articles, #26-30 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Articles, #31-33 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Articles, #34-37 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Articles, #38-39 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Articles, #39a-43 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Articles, #44-50 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Articles, #51-55 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Articles, #56-60 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Articles, #61-65 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Articles, #66-70 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Articles, #71-75 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Articles, #76-80 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Articles, #81-84 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Articles, #85 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
  - New Musical Scale - Bohlen-Pierce, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Percussive sensor paper (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - "The Digital Computer as a Musical Instrument," Scientific American, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Harmony and new musical scales, Royal Swedish Academy of Music, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Recollections of James Tenney, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "The Conductor Program and Mechanical Baton", 1987 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "The International Digital ElectroAcoustic Music Archive", 1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Future of Electronic Music, Bit Magazine (Japan), 1998 Aug (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Scanned Synthesis, ICMC, Berlin, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Parametric filters, SMAC 03, Stockholm, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Seasongs analysis (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Research
  - Filter design, 1989, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Radio baton wiring diagrams (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
  - Analog devices, ADuC702x ARM chip (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Catalog data, equipment, integrated circuit data, printed circuit information (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - Circuit diagrams (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
  - Cordless baton, radio baton, TI MSP-T5430M64 microprocessor (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Bell Labs
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1968 Jul-Nov (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1968 Nov - 1969 Apr (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1969 Mar-Jul (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1969 Aug-Oct (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1969 Nov - 1970 Feb (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1970 Feb-Jun (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1970 Jul-Oct (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1970 Nov - 1971 Jan (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1971 Jan-May (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1971 May-Oct (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1971 Sep - 1972 Jan (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1972 Mar-Nov (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1972 Nov - 1973 Sep (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1973 Sep - 1974 May (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1974 May 13 - 1976 Aug (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1976 Oct 7 - 1980 Feb (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1980 Mar - 1983 Nov (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Bell Labs notebook, 1983 Nov - 1986 Jun (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Bell Labs Center 1122 (Acoustical and Behavioral Research), private correspondence, 1963-1985 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- IRCAM
  - IRCAM, 1976 Aug (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - IRCAM, 1976 Dec (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - IRCAM, 1977 May (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - IRCAM, 1977 Jul (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - IRCAM, 1977 Dec (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - IRCAM, 1978 May (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - IRCAM, 1978 Dec (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - IRCAM, 1980 May (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - IRCAM, Boulez correspondence (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
  - Correspondence and reports (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Scores and arrangements
  - Henry Cowell, Rhythmicana (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Conductor program scores: Offenback, Rimsky-Korsakow, Schutz, Babbitt, Webern, Stravinsky, Amy Radunskaya (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Conductor program scores: Jaffe, Appleton, Getty, Schubert (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Scores: Mozart K453, Zurich pieces (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Scores: Brahms, Smith (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Conductor program scores: Bach, Benedict, Chopin, Schoenberg (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Conductor program scores: Vivaldi, Rachmaninoff (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Conductor program scores: Handel, Hayden, Purcell, Schumann, Josefina (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Conductor program scores: Mihran, Wold, Ussachevsku, Rossine, Saint-Saens (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Scores: Mozart (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
  - Conductor program scores: Theremin, Morrill, Molly Thompson (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Scores: Maureen - Camelot, Gershwin, Loewe, Saint-Saens (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Scores: Beethoven (Box 7, Folder 13-14)
  - Scores: Boulanger (Box 7, Folder 15-18)
- Biographical and personal materials
  - CVs, bibliographies, and photographs (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Literary efforts (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Clippings (Box 7, Folder 21-25)
- Audiovisual materials
  - Photographic negatives
    - 7094 computer (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Mathews and computer chess game in California, 1968 May (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Music V (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Shepard's tones (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Music IV (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Computers--general (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Computer composing (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Graphic comp. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Computer drawing (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Computer art (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Computer editing (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Conductor program (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Conversation study (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Fase (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - [unlabeled] (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Int. lullaby (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Groove (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
    - Neckhook, Mike (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Nonharmonic overtones (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Prog. inst. (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Remote access (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Scaling (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Small computers (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Speech syn. (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Timbre studies (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Violin (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Electronic violin, violin pitch detection (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Photographic slides
    - Computer art (Box 14)
    - Computer editing (Box 14)
    - Computer drawing (Box 14)
    - Graphic comp. (Box 14)
    - Remote access (Box 14)
    - Vocal tract inversion (Box 14)
    - Timbre studies (Box 14)
    - Vertical violin (Box 14)
    - RCA synthesizer (Box 14)
    - B-Line (Box 14)
    - Small computers (Box 14)
    - Groove (Box 14)
    - Music IV (Box 15)
    - Int. Lullaby (Box 15)
    - Comp. movie (Box 15)